James McKeen Cattell Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
James McKeen Cattell Papers 1835-1948 1896-1948
MSS15412
Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944
49,000 items
189 containers plus 1 oversize
76 linear feet
7 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Educator, editor, and psychologist. Correspondence, diaries, speeches, lectures, articles, notes, financial papers, biographical and genealogical material, family papers, printed matter, and other papers relating primarily to Cattell's professional and academic affiliations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949--Correspondence.; Bessey, Charles E. (Charles Edwin), 1845-1915--Correspondence.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942--Correspondence.; Boring, Edwin Garrigues, 1886-1968--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947--Correspondence.; Caldwell, Otis W. (Otis William), 1869-1947--Correspondence.; Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952--Correspondence.; Hall, Asaph, IV, 1859-1930--Correspondence.; Humphreys, W. J. (William Jackson), 1862-1949--Correspondence.; Huntington, Ellsworth, 1876-1947--Correspondence.; James, William, 1842-1910--Correspondence.; Jastrow, Joseph, 1863-1944--Correspondence.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931--Correspondence.; Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937--Correspondence.; Livingston, Burton E. (Burton Edward), 1875-1948--Correspondence.; Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924--Correspondence.; Lovejoy, Arthur O. (Arthur Oncken), 1873-1962--Correspondence.; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945--Correspondence.; Pearl, Raymond, 1879-1940--Correspondence.; Peirce, Charles S. (Charles Sanders), 1839-1914--Correspondence.; Seashore, Carl E. (Carl Emil), 1866-1949--Correspondence.; Thorndike, Edward L. (Edward Lee), 1874-1949--Correspondence.; Titchener, Edward Bradford, 1867-1927--Correspondence.; Watson, John B. (John Broadus), 1878-1958--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Association of University Professors.; Century Club (New York, N.Y.); Columbia University.; Psychological Corporation.; Science Press (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
American periodicals.; Psychology--Periodicals.; Psychology--Study and teaching.; Science--Periodicals.; Scientists--Biography.
Titles
American men of science.; American naturalist.; Popular science monthly (New York, N.Y.: 1900); School and society.; Science.
Occupations
Editors.; Educators.; Psychologists.
Acquisition Information
Part I of the papers of James McKeen Cattell was given to the Library of Congress in 1957 by his son, Jacques Cattell. A few items were given as an addition to Part I in 1965 by his wife, Quinta Cattell Kessel. Part II was given by McKeen Cattell, 1972-1975.
Additional Guides
A note about the James McKeen Cattell Papers appeared in the Library's Information Bulletin 17, no. 5: Feb. 3, 1955; and the material was described in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 15, no. 3: May 1958, 188-189, and 17, no. 3: May 1960, 170-174.
Transfers
Daguerreotypes and glass negatives have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of James McKeen Cattell are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on seven reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1860, May 25 Born, Easton, Pa.
1880 Graduated, Lafayette College, Easton, Pa.
1882 Studied at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1883 M.A., Lafayette College, Easton, Pa.
1883 1886 Research assistant to Wilhelm Wundt
1886 Ph.D., University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany
1886 1888 Fellow, St. John's College, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England, and lectured at Cambridge
1887 1891 Professor of psychology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1891 1917 Professor of psychology, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1894 1903 Editor, Psychological Review
1895 President, American Psychological Association
1900 1915 Editor, Popular Science Monthly
1904 1915 Editor, Science
1915 1943 Founder and editor, Scientific Monthly
1917 Dismissed from Columbia University, New York, N.Y., because of his opposition to the military draft in World War I
1944, Jan. 20 Died, Lancaster, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of James McKeen Cattell (1860-1944) span the years 1835-1948, with the bulk of the material from 1896 to 1948. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, speeches, lectures, articles, notes, financial papers, biographical and genealogical material, family papers, clippings, printed matter, and miscellaneous material. The papers are organized in two parts. Part I is organized in nine series: Journals; General Correspondence; Family Correspondence; Subject File; Speech, Article, and Book File; Photographs; Miscellany; Printed Matter; and Certificates, Diplomas, Charts, Graphs, and Tables (Oversize). Part II contains five series that complement the first portion: Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Subject File; Speech, Article, and Book File; and Miscellany.
The Cattell Papers relate primarily to Cattell's professional affiliations as an educator, university professor, psychologist, and editor and founder of scientific publications and periodicals. Prominent topics include organizations such as the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Psychological Corporation, American Association of University Professors, Century Club, and Columbia University; and his writings and editorial work for Science, Popular Science Monthly, School and Society, American Naturalist, American Men of Science, and Science Press. An extensive file treats his dismissal from Columbia University in 1917 because of his opposition to conscription in World War I.
The collection is rich in prominent correspondents in the scientific, political, and academic fields. A sampling of significant correspondents includes James Rowland Angell, Charles E. Bessey, Franz Boas, Edwin Garrigues Boring, Nicholas Murray Butler, Otis W. Caldwell, John Dewey, Asaph Hall, W. J. Humphreys, Ellsworth Huntington, William James, Joseph Jastrow, David Starr Jordan, Vernon L. Kellogg, Burton E. Livingston, Jacques Loeb, Arthur O. Lovejoy, Thomas Hunt Morgan, Raymond Pearl, Charles S. Peirce, Carl E. Seashore, Edward L. Thorndike, Edward Titchener, and John B. Watson.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in two parts composed of fourteen series:
Part I:
Journals, 1874-1880
General Correspondence, 1884-1944
Family Correspondence, 1880-1944
Subject File
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1874-1946
Photographs
Miscellany
Printed Matter, 1869-1948
Certificates, Diplomas, Charts, Graphs, and Tables, 1880-1937
Part II:
Family Correspondence, 1835-1922
General Correspondence, 1880-1940
Subject File, 1890-1936
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1875-1935
Miscellany, 1839-1940
Container List
- Part I: Journals, 1874-1880 (Box 1)
  Childhood journals.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1874-1875, 1880 (Box 1)
- Part I: General Correspondence, 1884-1944 (Box 1-49)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Abbe, Cleveland, 1896-1909 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, A. C., 1897-1911
  - Achilles, Paul S., 1927-1942
  - Adams, Charles C., 1903-1937
  - Adams, Frank D., 1897-1909
  - Adler, Cyrus, 1897-1907
  - Agassiz, Alexander, 1897-1907
  - Alexander, Jerome, 1923-1945
  - Allen, E. W., 1903-1905
  - Allen, J. A., 1897-1910
  - Ames, J. S., 1899-1906
  - Ami, Henry M., 1899-1908
  - Anderson, Robert, 1907-1908
  - Andrews, E. A., 1898-1910
  - Angell, James Rowland, 1894-1944
  - Armsby, Henry P., 1903-1909
  - Armstrong, A. C., 1894-1903
  - Arnold, Felix, 1903-1908
  - Arnot, Raymond H., 1908-1909
  - Ashby, George H., 1900-1906
  - Atkinson, Edward, 1900-1904 (Box 2)
  - Atkinson, George F., 1897-1901
  - Ayers, Howard, 1900-1904
  - “Aar-Aye” miscellaneous
  - Bagley, William C., 1905-1944 (Box 3)
  - Bain, Joseph H., 1902-1906
  - Baker, Frank C., 1898-1908
  - Baldwin, J. Mark, 1893-1908
  - Bancroft, Wilder D., 1897-1930
  - Barker, Lewellys F., 1900-1908
  - Barnard, E. E., 1898-1909
  - Barnes, C. R., 1898-1905
  - Barrows, Albert A., 1940
  - Barrows, Franklin W., 1897-1902
  - Barsky, Edward, 1939-1941
  - Bartech, Paul, 1940
  - Barus, C., 1897-1911
  - Baskerville, Charles, 1898-1909 (Box 4)
  - Bateson, W., 1907-1909
  - Bather, F. A., 1898-1907
  - Bauer, L. A., 1899-1909
  - Bawden, H. Heath, 1899-1921
  - Beal, W. J., 1900-1911
  - Beebe, William H. H., 1897-1901
  - Bell, A. N., 1904
  - Bell, Alexander Graham, 1899-1908
  - Benjamin, Marcus, 1898-1910
  - Berry, Edward W., 1900-1941
  - Bessey, Charles E., 1897-1910
  - Beyer, Louellen R., 1939-1943
  - Bierly, H. Elmer, 1899-1909
  - Bigelow, Frank H., 1899-1910
  - Bigelow, Maurice A., 1900-1911
  - Bigelow, S. Lawrence, 1904-1907
  - Billings, J. S., 1892-1909
  - Birge, Raymond T., 1940
  - Birkhoff, George D., 1940-1944
  - Blakeslee, Albert F., 1906-1941 (Box 5)
  - Boas, Franz, 1897-1941
  - Bogert, Marston T., 1899-1944
  - Bolton, Frederick E., 1897-1945
  - Bolton, H. Carrington, 1897-1903
  - Bolton, Thaddeus L., 1901-1908
  - Bolza, Oskar, 1898-1909
  - Bond, Frank, 1903
  - Bond, Frederick D., 1907-1909
  - Boring, Edward Garrigues, 1929-1940
  - Bowditch, H. P., 1898-1905
  - Bowen, Edwin W., 1904-1907
  - Branner, J. C., 1897-1911
  - Breese, B. B., 1899-1905
  - Breit, Gregory, 1940
  - Brett, George P., 1896-1939
  - Brewster, William T., 1907-1910
  - Brigham, Albert P., 1899-1909
  - Brinton, Daniel G., 1894-1907
  - Bristol, C. L., 1897-1908
  - Britton, N. L., 1899-1910
  - Brooks, Alfred H., 1907-1907
  - Brooks, Robert C., 1906-1909
  - Brooks, W. K., 1900-1903
  - Brown, Charles W., 1907
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1907
  - Brown, Ernest W., 1898-1910
  - Brown, F. C., 1907-1940
  - Bruner, Frank G., 1903-1909 (Box 6)
  - Brush, Charles F., 1897-1899
  - Bryan, Kirk, 1930-1941
  - Bryan, William L., 1894-1905
  - Buchner, Edward F., 1897-1909
  - Bumpers, H. C., 1897-1909
  - Bunker, Frank F., 1930-1938
  - Burgess, A. F., 1905-1909
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1896-1911
  - “Baa-Bat” miscellaneous
  - “Bak-Blu” miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - “Boa-Byr” miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Caldwell, Otis W., 1911-1946
  - Calkins, Gary N., 1896-1909 (Box 9)
  - Calkins, Mary W., 1894-1911
  - Canfield, James H., 1899-1907
  - Cannon, W. B., 1908-1940
  - Carpenter, George R., 1899-1909
  - Castle, W. E., 1902-1909
  - Chamberlin, T. C., 1897-1909
  - Clark, Austin H., 1907-1941
  - Clark, F. W., 1900-1909
  - Clark, Herbert L., 1901-1909
  - Clark, John M., 1899-1919
  - Clark, William B., 1897-1908
  - Clayton, H. H., 1900-1906
  - Cleveland, Newcombe, 1923-1944
  - Clifton, Richard S., 1901-1907 (Box 10)
  - Cockerell, T. D. A., 1899-1931
  - Cole, Alfred D., 1904-1909
  - Cole, F. N., 1897-1907
  - Compton, Karl T., 1927-1940
  - Comstock, George C., 1898-1909
  - Conklin, E. G., 1898-1944
  - Coulter, John M., 1899-1919
  - Coville, Frederick V., 1899-1927
  - Cowles, Henry C., 1904-1931
  - Cox, Charles F., 1899-1909
  - Crampton, Henry E., 1902-1908
  - Crew, Henry, 1900-1940
  - Crook, A. R., 1902-1909
  - Curtis, Steven, 1899-1904
  - “Cad-Cat” miscellaneous
  - “Cha-Cos” miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - “Cot-Cut” miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Dall, William, 1898-1909
  - Dana, Charles L., 1899-1906
  - Dana, E. S., 1899-1908
  - Dandeno, J. B., 1901-1909
  - Davenport, Charles B., 1897-1944
  - Davies, Henry, 1899-1902
  - Davis, Bradley M., 1897-1909
  - Davis, Watson, 1925-1944
  - Davis, William H., 1900-1932
  - Davis, William M., 1897-1910 (Box 13)
  - Day, William S., 1899-1907
  - Dean, Bashford, 1898-1909
  - Dean, John C., 1902-1909
  - Dearborn, George V. N., 1897-1926
  - Dearborn, Walter F., 1904-1909
  - Delabarre, E. B., 1894-1909
  - Deland, Fred, 1906-1909
  - Derby, George, 1930-1938
  - Dewey, John, 1893-1937
  - Dexter, Edwin G., 1899-1940
  - Dietz, David, 1932-1944
  - Dodge, Raymond, 1899-1923
  - Dodge, Richard E., 1897-1932
  - Donaldson, Henry H., 1893-1909
  - Donohoe, John P., 1907-1942
  - Duggan, Stephen, 1937-1940
  - “Dab-Deg” miscellaneous
  - “Del-Dyk” miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Eastman, C. R., 1897-1907 (Box 15)
  - Edmunds, Charles K., 1901-1909
  - Edwards, Charles L., 1900-1909
  - Egbert, James C., 1906-1909
  - Eichelberger, W. S., 1901-1906
  - Eigenmann, Carl H., 1899-1906
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1900-1907
  - Engelmann, George J., 1900-1907
  - “Eag-Exe” miscellaneous
  - Fairchild, H. L., 1898-1932 (Box 16)
  - Fancher, B. H., 1901-1909
  - Farquhar, John W., 1899-1942
  - Farlow, W. G., 1898-1909
  - Fernow, B. E., 1897-1905
  - Fisher, George F., 1897-1905
  - Fisher, Irving, 1905-1909
  - Fiske, Thomas S., 1898-1910
  - Fleming, John R., 1902-1940
  - Fletcher, Alice C., 1897-1910
  - Flexner, Simon, 1898-1937
  - Forbes, S. A., 1900-1909
  - Franklin, C. Ladd, 1894-1908
  - Franklin, W. S., 1897-1910
  - Franz, Shepherd, 1897-1907
  - Freer, Paul C., 1898-1908
  - Frost, Edwin B., 1898-1932
  - Fuller, Myron L., 1903-1909
  - Fullerton, George S., 1894-1909
  - “Fab-Fur” miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Gage, Simon H., 1897-1926 (Box 18)
  - Gager, C. Stuart, 1906-1937
  - Galloway, B. T., 1899-1905
  - Ganong, William F., 1899-1910
  - Gardiner, Edward G., 1897-1905
  - Gardiner, H. N., 1894-1907
  - Garrison, F. H., 1908-1909
  - Geare, R. I., 1900-1908
  - Geis, William J., 1901-1930
  - Gibbs, Wolcott, 1897-1902
  - Giddings, Franklin H., 1899-1932
  - Gilbert, G. K., 1896-1907
  - Gill, Laura D., 1901-1907
  - Gill, Theodore, 1897-1909
  - Goetze, Frederick A., 1899-1908
  - Goode, J. Paul, 1900-1908
  - Goodspeed, Arthur W., 1901-1931
  - Goodrich, A. G., 1899-1901
  - Gould, George M., 1902-1909
  - Gratacap, L. P., 1900-1908
  - Gregory, William K., 1901-1945
  - Griggs, Robert F., 1908-1909 (Box 19)
  - Gudger, E. W., 1905-1945
  - Gulliver, F. P., 1897-1909
  - Guthe, Karl E., 1905-1908
  - “Gab-Gyo” miscellaneous
  - Hadley, Phillip B., 1907-1909 (Box 20)
  - Hague, Arnold, 1897-1909
  - Hale, George E., 1898-1909
  - Hall, Asaph, 1899-1906
  - Hall, Edwin H., 1899-1909
  - Hall, G. Stanley, 1898-1909
  - Hallock, William, 1897-1909
  - Halsted, George B., 1897-1907
  - Hargitt, Charles W., 1899-1909
  - Harper, Roland M., 1902-1931
  - Harris, E. P., 1901-1903
  - Harris, R. A., 1898-1909
  - Harrison, Ross G., 1902-1940
  - Hart and Vonarx, 1905-1909
  - Hatcher, J. B., 1899-1903
  - Haupt, Lewis M., 1903-1906
  - Hay, O. P., 1897-1909
  - Hayford, John F., 1899-1910
  - Hedrick, E. R., 1902-1934
  - Herdman, W. A., 1898-1907
  - Herrick, C. Judson, 1894-1899
  - Herrick, Francis H., 1897-1909
  - Herrick, Glen W., 1901-1940
  - Hewett, Edgar L., 1904-1905
  - Hibben, John G., 1897-1906
  - Hill, A. Ross, 1900-1905
  - Hill, Robert T., 1900-1907
  - Hinrichs, Gustavus, 1903-1909
  - Hitchcock, A. S., 1903-1933
  - Hobbs, William H., 1899-1936
  - Hodge, F. W., 1897-1908
  - Holden, Edward S., 1897-1909
  - Holland, W. J., 1899-1909 (Box 21)
  - Hollick, Arthur, 1898-1908
  - Hollingworth, H. L., 1906-1944
  - Holmes, S. J., 1907-1909
  - Holmes, W. H., 1897-1909
  - Horstmann, E., 1898-1903
  - Houck, George M., 1936-1940
  - Houston, Henry E., 1897-1906
  - Hovey, Edmund O., 1900-1909
  - Howard, L. O., 1897-1927
  - Howe, Charles S., 1901-1909
  - Howe, Joseph L., 1895-1907
  - Howell, William H., 1897-1904
  - Howison, G. H., 1898-1902
  - Hoyt, John W., 1901
  - Hrdlicka, A., 1902-1941
  - Huber, G. Carl, 1902-1909
  - Huey, Edmund B., 1897-1909
  - Hughes, Percy, 1902-1937
  - Humphreys, Alec C., 1902-1906
  - Humphreys, W. J., 1899-1944
  - Huntington, Ellsworth, 1907-1936
  - Hyslop, James H., 1898-1913
  - “Haa-Hen” miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - “Her-Hyl” miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - “Iac-Ive” miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - Jackman, Wilbur S., 1898-1906
  - Jackson, Dugald C., 1900-1937
  - Jacoby, Harold, 1898-1908
  - James, William, 1893-1910
  - Jastrow, Joseph, 1894-1940, undated
  - Jeffrey, Edward, 1905-1927
  - Jelliffe, Smith E., 1900-1908
  - Jennings, Herbert S., 1897-1922
  - Jesse, R. H., 1899-1905
  - Jewett, Frank B., 1930-1942
  - Johnson, Douglass W., 1900-1941
  - Johnson, Duncan S., 1904-1909
  - Jones, Elmer E., 1901-1931
  - Jones, Harry C., 1900-1907
  - Jordon, David S., 1899-1909
  - Jordon, Edwin O., 1897-1908
  - Judd, Charles H., 1897-1934 (Box 25)
  - “Jac-Jus” miscellaneous
  - Keasbey, Lindley M., 1901-1906
  - Keen, W. W., 1900-1923
  - Kellerman, W. A., 1899-1906
  - Kellogg, Vernon L., 1899-1909
  - Kemp, George T., 1904-1910
  - Kemp, J. F., 1899-1909
  - Kennedy, Francis, 1898-1900
  - Kennelly, A. E., 1901-1908
  - Kent, William, 1904-1909
  - Keppel, Frederick P.
    - 1900-1903
    - 1904-1941 (Box 26)
  - King, A. F. A., 1901-1909
  - King, F. H., 1903-1908
  - Kingsley, J. S., 1898-1909
  - Kirkpatrick, E. A., 1903-1905
  - Kline, Linus W., 1890-1908
  - Knower, H. McE., 1900-1908
  - Kober, George M., 1897-1906
  - Koford, Charles A., 1897-1910
  - Kraemer, Henry, 1899-1906
  - Kremers, Edward, 1905-1909
  - Kunz, George F., 1897-1931
  - Kuntz, George F., 1905-1931
  - “Kad-Kyl” miscellaneous
  - Ladd, George T., 1893-1909 (Box 27)
  - Lamb, D. C., 1897-1909
  - Lane, Alfred C., 1903
  - Lay, Wilfrid, 1899-1903
  - Lee, Frederic S., 1899-1909
  - Leuba, James H., 1899-1933
  - Lewis, Frederic T., 1906-1940
  - Libbey, William, 1897-1906
  - Lindley, E. H., 1901-1931
  - Link, Henry C., 1937-1942
  - Livingston, Burton E., 1903-1944
  - Lloyd, Alfred H., 1897-1903
  - Lloyd, Francis E., 1899-1908
  - Locy, William A., 1899-1909
  - Loeb, Morris, 1899-1909
  - Long, John H., 1901-1907
  - Lord, Herbert G., 1901-1909
  - Lough, James E., 1899-1926
  - Lovejoy, Arthur O., 1904-1909
  - Low, Seth, 1897-1910
  - Lucas, F. A., 1897-1909
  - Luck, J. Murray, 1930-1939
  - Lull, Richard S., 1904-1910
  - Lyon, T. Lyttleton, 1908-1909
  - “Lac-Lyo” miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - Macallum, A. B., 1897-1908 (Box 29)
  - McAndrew, William, 1928-1937
  - MacBride, Thomas H., 1902-1908
  - McClendon, J. F., 1909-1932
  - MacCracken, John H., 1903-1934
  - MacCracken, T. C., 1932-1941
  - MacCurdy, George G., 1899-1909
  - MacDonald, Arthur, 1894-1909
  - MacDougal, D. T., 1897-1921
  - McGee, W. J., 1897-1902
  - McKee, Ralph H., 1906-1909
  - McKinley, Earl B., 1936-1938
  - McLaughlin, Allen J., 1902-1907
  - Macmillan Co., 1899-1905, 1940
  - MacMillan Conway, 1898-1903
  - McMurrick, J. Mayfair, 1900-1909
  - McMurtrie, William, 1900-1909
  - McPherson, William, 1901-1910
  - Magie, W. F., 1900-1909 (Box 30)
  - Magruder, William T., 1904-1908
  - Major, David R., 1899-1908
  - Mann, C. R., 1902-1910
  - Manson, Marsden, 1904-1909
  - Mark, E. L., 1898-1909
  - Marlatt, C. L., 1898-1904
  - Marsh, Howard D., 1904-1907
  - Marsh, M. C., 1902-1909
  - Marshall, Henry R., 1894-1909
  - Marx, Guido H., 1908-1909
  - Mason, O. T., 1897-1905
  - Mason, W. P., 1897-1909
  - Mast, S. O., 1907-1941
  - Mathews, Albert P., 1902-1908
  - Mathews, Dean C., 1907-1908
  - Mayer, Alfred G., 1903-1910
  - Mead, A. D., 1900-1905
  - Meltzer, S. J., 1901-1908
  - Mendel, Lafayette B., 1901-1928
  - Mendenhall, T. C., 1897-1909
  - Mercer, Henry C., 1897-1899
  - Merriman, Mansfield, 1897-1908
  - Merritt, Ernest, 1898-1903
  - Messenger, J. F., 1901-1940
  - Metcalf, Maynard H., 1901-1909
  - Meyer, Adolph, 1903-1909
  - Meyer, Max F., 1902-1932
  - Mezes, Sidney E., 1894-1906
  - Miles, Walter R., 1933-1940
  - Miller, Dickinson S., 1897-1910
  - Miller, Gerrit S., Jr., 1898-1903
  - Miller, Newman, 1901-1909
  - Millikan, Robert A., 1904-1940
  - Miner, James B., 1901-1910
  - Minot, Charles S., 1897-1909 (Box 31)
  - Montague, W. P., 1899-1910
  - Montgomery, Thomas H., Jr., 1901-1909
  - Moody, Roy L., 1907-1909
  - Morgan, T. H., 1902-1941
  - Moritz, Arthur M., 1931-1935
  - Morse, Max, 1903-1909
  - Moulton, F. R., 1936-1945
  - Muensterberg, Hugo, 1893-1910
  - Munroe, Charles E., 1898-1909
  - Murrill, W. A., 1906-1909
  - “Mac” miscellaneous
  - “McA-Min” miscellaneous (Box 32)
  - “Mir-Myc” miscellaneous (Box 33)
  - Nelson, Charles E., 1937-1941
  - Neumann Brothers, 1902-1907
  - New Era Printing Co., 1902-1910
  - Newbold, William R., 1898-1909
  - Newcomb, S., 1896-1909
  - Newcombe, Frederick C., 1900-1908
  - Newell, W. W., 1898-1906
  - Nichols, E. F., 1899-1909
  - Nichols, Edward L., 1900-1910 (Box 34)
  - Norton, J. Pease, 1907-1909
  - Noyes, Arthur A., 1901-1921
  - Noyes, William A., 1898-1931
  - Nutting, C. C., 1897-1904
  - “Nac-Nut” miscellaneous
  - O'Reilly, M. F., 1901-1902
  - Orser, Levi, 1900-1901
  - Ortmann, A. E., 1897-1909
  - Osborn, Henry F., 1897-1941
  - O'Shea, M. V., 1898-1909
  - Ostwald, Wilhelm, 1905-1906
  - Owen, George N., 1901-1902
  - “Oas-Ozd” miscellaneous
  - Packard, A. S., 1898-1903 (Box 35)
  - Palmer, Charles S., 1899-1912
  - Parker, George H., 1897-1944
  - Parsons, Charles L., 1904-1909
  - Pearl, Raymond, 1900-1944
  - Peckham, S. F., 1900-1903
  - Peirce, Charles S., 1898-1906
  - Peirce, George J., 1903-1909
  - Penhallow, D. P., 1905-1909
  - Perry, Edward D., 1896-1908
  - Peterson, Frederick, 1900-1907
  - Pickering, Edward C., 1898-1908
  - Pierce, A. H., 1898-1909
  - Pillsbury, W. B., 1890-1944
  - Poffenberger, A. T., 1932-1944
  - Pond, Raymond H., 1905-1909
  - Poor, Charles L., 1899-1906
  - Porter, W. T., 1897-1909
  - Pound, Roscoe, 1925
  - Pratt, Henry S., 1900-1909
  - Preston, E. D., 1898-1901
  - Pritchett, Henry S., 1898-1910
  - Prosser, Charles S., 1897-1905
  - Prudden, T. Mitchell, 1897-1910
  - Putnam, F. W., 1897-1908
  - Putnam's Sons, G. P., 1901-1904
  - “Pac-Pat” miscellaneous
  - “Pau-Pyl” miscellaneous (Box 36)
  - “Qua-Qui” miscellaneous
  - Ramaley, Francis, 1899-1908
  - Rathbun, Richard, 1900-1908
  - Reichert, Edward T., 1900-1909
  - Reid, Harry F., 1899-1909
  - Reighard, Jacob, 1899-1909
  - Remsen, Ira, 1897-1908
  - Renouf, Edward, 1900-1909
  - Rhine, J. B., 1937-1938
  - Rice, Calvin W., 1902-1931
  - Richards, Theodore W., 1898-1909
  - Richardson, Clifford, 1901-1909 (Box 37)
  - Ripley, William Z., 1897-1900
  - Ritter, William E., 1899-1940
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1899-1931
  - Rockwell, Alfred E., 1903-1908
  - Roe, William J., 1903-1908
  - Rogers, Howard J., 1899-1906
  - Rood, Ogden N., 1897-1901
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919), 1897-1908
  - Rosa, Edward B., 1900-1907
  - Rosanoff, M. A., 1909-1940
  - Rotch, Abbott Lawrence, 1897-1908
  - Royce, Josiah, 1898-1908
  - Ruger, Henry A., 1901-1909
  - Russell, Israel C., 1897-1905
  - Russell, James E., 1896-1908
  - Ruthven, Alexander G., 1907-1939
  - Rutter, Cloud, 1900-1902
  - “Rab-Rob” miscellaneous
  - “Rol-Ryk” miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - Sabin, Florence R., 1904-1937
  - Salisbury, Rollins D., 1897-1908
  - Sanford, Edmund C., 1896-1914
  - Scharbule, J. M., 1906-1909
  - Schneider, Albert, 1901-1908
  - Schuchert, Charles, 1899-1940
  - Scott, Charles P. G., 1903-1926
  - Scott, W. B., 1899-1909
  - Scott, W. E. D., 1901-1905
  - Scripture, E. W., 1890-1909
  - Seashore, C. E., 1899-1937
  - Sedgwick, William T., 1897-1909
  - See, T. J. J., 1899-1909
  - Sellards, E. H., 1904-1907
  - Sharp, Benjamin F., 1898-1904